Most AI begins composing from one prompt.
But difficult decisions rarely live in one message.
They live in history: who is involved, what happened before,
what changed, and what remains uncertain.
Second Mind, by Cognisyn, is an evidence-linked cognitive companion
built around one principle: context before composition.
Context can enter naturally—as a message, note, event, or screenshot.
The current prototype files it into an editable relationship graph
and a chronological situation timeline.
In this fictional case, Vargus records five events
involving Benedict and Gertrude.
The graph keeps relationships separate,
while the timeline preserves sequence and source.
Merlin does not declare a motive.
It tests competing explanations.
Here, romantic tension reaches an illustrative forty-nine percent,
while non-romantic friction remains close at forty-three percent.
Every update links to evidence, discloses its assumptions,
and lets the user downweight, reject, or correct an inference.
The difference appears at the moment of action.
An isolated model responds to Benedict's request literally.
Second Mind offers several context-aware paths without presenting
romance, conflict, or personality as fact. The user chooses.
Before sending, Perspective Simulation rehearses how Benedict
might read the selected response: its literal meaning,
a possible emotional interpretation, and misunderstanding risk.
It models perspectives without claiming access
to someone else's mind.
We also tested the wider premise—that fuller context can improve
forecasting—on 4,188 ConvoKit conversations,
with 840 held out and zero paid API calls.
The results are a research baseline, never a tool for judging people.
I used Codex with GPT-5.6 to design, implement, and test
the capture pipeline, relationship graph,
epistemic result contract, and evaluation suite.
The optional live reasoning path uses GPT-5.6 through the OpenAI
Responses API; this judge demo remains reproducible without a private key.
Next, the same architecture can support voice capture, Push to Think,
Reflection Mode, and private earbud delivery on existing hardware.
Second Mind does not become the decision-maker.
It preserves the evidence, exposes the inference,
and returns the judgment to the person.
Context before composition. Think clearly. Stay yours.